# **Nathaniel Flores**

## Front-End Developer

floresnathanie183@gmail.com

# Summary

I'm looking for a position on a team as a front-end developer to help build web applications with the aim to connect business goals to user's needs therefore making things more efficient.

For the past 10 years I have built a career in retail management and customer service. I have always had a passion and curiosity for information technology and computers and how it relates to business models and goals. At the beginning of this year I decided to make a change. I really wanted to challenge myself and get out of my comfort zone. I started to research different areas in IT and fell into many hours of coding tutorials. It was then that I realized how much I love the craft of programming. I think it's amazing that what I can build can solve many problems facing peoples lives and businesses today all from a small device in your pocket. That is something I want to be a part of.

I am a graduate from the Front End Engineering program at The Iron Yard. I have a degree in International Business. My experience in management gives me the unique ability to remain communicative, flexible and open minded on a dynamic team to efficiently reach diverse solutions. My time at The Iron Yard gives me the confidence to break down problems systematically and to quickly learn different tools, libraries and frameworks to get solutions in a constantly changing environment. I continue to learn everyday I code and the projects at my website nathanielflores.com will show my progression from day one to the creation of a my first full stack application.

# Experience

## Front-End Developer at The Iron Yard

May 2016 - August 2016 (4 months)

- Developed fully responsive web applications using HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap, JavaScript, jQuery, APIs, MVC and Flux architecture (BackboneJS and ReactJS), API/RESTful services, MongoDB, Express, and NodeJS
- -My biggest achievement to date is Vinyl Pi, a full stack trading application for vinyl aficionados. Users are able to trade records and share their story about how they got into collecting records, inspiring further exploration into under-appreciated genres and record labels. I built it using JavaScript, HTML, CSS and React on the client side and Mongoose, Express, MongoDb on the server side. I utilized a flux architecture created with Underscore, Backbone and jQuery

#### BASIC TOOLS:

-	Ι	use	these	basic	tools	for	my	everyday	workflow

Basic terminal usage

GitHub basics

**Basic SSH** 

Sublime Text Editor

#### HTML5/CSS3:

-I have exposure to user interface and user experience interactions and layouts that are fully responsive by understanding what the user and client needs are through meticulous wire-framing, prototyping and development planning

Sass

Scss

Skeleton

Bootstrap

Responsive design with CSS

#### JAVASCRIPT:

-I started out building my first projects using pure JavaScript and as my applications became more complex I started to implement different architectures, frameworks and libraries

Backbone.js

React.js

jQuery

Underscore

MVC architecture

Flux architecture

Browserify

Bower/package management

ES6/ES2015 (Babel)

#### NODE.JS:

-I have exposure to server side programming. For my app, Vinyl Pi, I wrote my own API and created a database to save user information

**Express** 

Mongoose

MongoDB

MongoChef

PostMan

API's/RESTful services/GET POST PUT DELETE requests

Heroku web platform

Understanding of how the client and server talk to each other

#### General Manager at Teavana

September 2011 - August 2015 (4 years)

- Coach and mentor partners on sales process and core beliefs.
- Recruit, hire and train potential candidates for new store opening (Deerbrook Mall '12).
- Train and follow up with visual team lead to ensure proper merchandising and cleanliness.
- Create training plans to support changes in sales processes and core beliefs.
- Maintain clear communication and follow up with management team and AM to support all store operations.
- Provide and receive feedback to creatively solve problems

#### Assistant Store Manager at Starbucks

June 2007 - November 2011 (4 years 6 months)

- Coach and mentor partners to achieve excellent customer service, coffee standards.
- Plan and supervise shifts to support store operations and meet sanitation standards.
- Analyze sales reports to increase profits and control cost.
- Build and maintain customer and co-worker relationships.
- Manage a variety of situations independently and judiciously to resolve difficult service issues.
- Accountable for cash controller responsibilities and training new employees to be successful.
- Execute marketing plans for seasonal and promotional products.

#### Manager Assistant at Enterprise Rent-A-Car

September 2005 - June 2007 (1 year 10 months)

- Plan and supervise shifts to support store operations.
- Analyze sales reports to increase profits and control cost.
- Build and maintain customer and co-worker relationships.
- Manage a variety of situations independently and judiciously to resolve difficult service issues.
- Accountable for cash controller responsibilities and training new employees to be successful.

Execute marketing plans.

- Handle accounts receivable for outstanding balances

# Skills & Expertise

**JavaScript** 

**HTML** 

**CSS** 

Node.js

Express.js

React.js

MongoDB

Backbone.js

**jQuery** 

basic terminal usage

GitHub basics

responsive design with CSS

**MVC/Flux architecture** 

Wireframing

**Prototyping** 

**Development Planning** 

**ES6/ES2015 (Babel)** 

**Underscore.js** 

**Sublime Text Editor** 

basic SSH

**Skeleton** 

Scss

Sass

Management

**Customer Service** 

**Coaching** 

**Recruiting** 

Sales

**Retail Sales** 

Communication

**Organization Skills** 

**Public Speaking** 

Leadership

## Education

#### The Iron Yard

Non-degree program, Front-end engineering, 2016 - 2016

Grade: pass

#### The University of Texas at Arlington

Bachelor's degree Business Administration, International Business, 2001 - 2005

Grade: 3.528 Cum Laude

Activities and Societies: Intramural sports

**Grapevine Highschool** 

1997 - 2001

Activities and Societies: Basketball, Tennis, Golf and Piano

## **Organizations**

#### Filipino Young Professionals

October 2014 to Present

#### **Young Catholic Professionals**

## Volunteer Experience

#### **Volunteer at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)**

September 2015 - Present

Helped to cheer on and motivate bike riders in support of the American Diabetes Association. We also provided refreshments and snacks to keep riders hydrated and energized.

# Helped renovate homeless shelter to make more livable and lively at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)

March 2015 - Present

We were able to re-paint a homeless shelter located in downtown Houston for Charities of the Catholic Diocese of Houston-Galveston. This made the environment more livable and welcoming to those in need.

#### **Volunteer at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)**

March 2016 - Present

In support of Easter Seals Greater Houston - Respite Department and Andi Fry, the program coordinator at 1600 Lake Front Circle, The Woodlands, TX 77380, 281-838-9050 x315. 5.5 hours.

Acted as a buddy for children with disabilities, so that the parents can enjoy a break and have time to themselves.

## Volunteer at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)

September 2016 - Present

In support of Easter Seals Greater Houston - Respite Department and Andi Fry, the program coordinator at 1600 Lake Front Circle, The Woodlands, TX 77380, 281-838-9050 x315. 5.5 hours.

Acted as a buddy for children with disabilities, so that the parents can enjoy a break and have time to themselves.

#### **Volunteer at The Filipino Young Professionals of Houston (FYP)**

April 2016 - Present

## Languages

## **English**

#### **Publications**

#### "Experiences in Programming and Human minds All Rapped Up in Life"

Medium.com March 23, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

This one is an introduction to my experiences in technology and programming, specifically in JavaScript, from ground zero

#### "The Command Line"

Medium.com March 29, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

This one is about the command line. What it is and how it pertains to coding

## "Learning Git and Other things and Attention Deficit Disorders"

Medium.com March 30, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

This one is about my experience learning Git and the realization afterwards of the feeling of learning multiple languages and tools in web development

#### Takeaway #1

Medium.com July 29, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

This is the first in a series of useful ramblings to educate those first starting their journey into coding and for my own progress tracking as I work through different projects and experiences.

## Takeaway #2

Medium.com August 17, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

Takeaway series continued..

## Takeaway #3

Medium.com August 18, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

Takeaway series continued..

#### Takeaway #4

Medium.com August 19, 2016

Authors: Nathaniel Flores

Takeaway series continued..

# **Nathaniel Flores**

# Front-End Developer

floresnathaniel83@gmail.com



Contact Nathaniel on LinkedIn